Msc (Hons), Bsc (Hons), CSM

<u>jiegaouk@gmail.com</u> http://jerrygaolondon.github.io

General

- I'm specializing in a wide range of computational techniques for the detection of disinformation and misinformation. With over a decade of hands-on experience in large-scale distributed systems and several years in mobile app development, I possess a solid technical foundation.
- In my role as a **Research Scientist**, I bring more than ten years of experience in academic research in **Natural Language Processing** (NLP) and **Social Media Analytics**. I have authored over 10 publications in prestigious conferences and journals (e.g., ICLR, KDD, ASONAM, LREC, IEEE/ACM, etc) with **h-index and i10-index 9**. My expertise encompasses **information system architecture**, **AI algorithm optimization**, NLP, machine learning, **knowledge engineering** and **knowledge graph** technology with good hands-on experience and knowledge of the following languages and formats: SPARQL 1.1, RDF / RDFS, OWL, SKOS. Ref.: ORCID: 0000-0002-3610-8748, RID (Web of Science ResearcherID): AAB-4270-2020; Google ScholarID: 1zoqXaMAAAAJ
- I am proficient in both traditional and cutting-edge NLP and machine learning techniques, utilizing libraries such as Pytorch, Keras, spaCy, NLTK, and more. Furthermore, I am an adept software developer with a background in developing multi-tier applications in JEE, Node JS, and Python.
- My experience extends to cloud technologies like AWS and GCP, ETL processes, Big Data technologies such as MapReduce and Spark, and graph technology. I have also made contributions to open-source tools and frameworks.
- Earlier in my career, I was involved in the development of enterprise applications and web systems, catering to
 clients from Fortune 500 companies, as well as banks, insurance companies, and government entities. I gained rich
 experience in fundamental web technologies like HTML, JSP, CSS, XML, JSON, JavaScript, and Ajax, applying
 various design patterns and frameworks.
- In the academic realm, I have actively contributed to the field by serving as a reviewer for esteemed conferences and journals, including ACL Rolling Review (ARR), EMNLP, Plos One, Journal of NLP, and Journal of Intelligent Systems, showcasing my dedication to advancing our knowledge in this domain.

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Staff Engineer, Logically AI Senior Research Engineer, Logically AI May 2022 – Present July 2020 – May 2022

- With extensive expertise and involvement in misinformation AI, I lead a collaborative AI team dedicated to
 fact-checking, evidence retrieval techniques, rumor resolution on social media, and information credibility
 assessment. My work encompasses computational methods for analyzing disinformation, detecting coordinated
 inauthentic behavior on social media, and addressing online threats and influences.
- I am also skilled and actively leads in various projects and people management, strategic planning/direction, human-and-model-in-the-loop strategy, machine learning engineering standards, test-driven ML framework, data quality methodologies, write-up of scientific papers and company white papers, research proposals, and cross-disciplinary & cross-functional collaboration (with sales, OSINT experts, fact-checkers, product).
- This technical lead role focusses more on human(client/user)-centered AI architecture and pipeline
 planning. This entails a thorough understanding of end-to-end ML and deep learning workload workflows, with
 expertise in the components and architectural trade-offs inherent in data management (e.g., with DVC, GCP
 Bucket), governance, model building (e.g., Mlflow, model registry), and the deployment and production
 workflows of AI

Research Associate, OAK Group, University of Sheffield

Mar 2014 – June 2020

- Involved in various research project, including European Foundation funded Europeana DSI-3, two
 European FP7 projects (WeSenselt and SETA), two Innovative UK (prev. TSB) funded projects
 (SPEEAK-PC 101947 with TATA Steel UK and KTP project 007326 for ActiveStandards, the market-leading SaaS platform), three industry/government/academic collaboration projects (with K-Now,
 JustGiving, MoveMore and Active10)
- Doctoral Candidate in NLP and computational terminology
- 2 years as Teaching Assistant for "COM3504 The Intelligent Web" module (>70 students)
- Invited speaker/presentation (4 times) in international conference / workshop
- Leading the development and am the manager of the scalable, computational and economically efficient infrastructure that collects the data in large-scale from the mobile phones in EU project SETA and Active10 projects (over 129K monthly active users and over 600,000 downloads over past 10 months) on behalf of Public Health England.

- co-PI of Europeana Digital Service Infrastructure (DSI) DSI-3 (addendum project) for Metis and Solr services
- leading & coordinating the research for work package (WP) 3 ("Data Representation, Mining & Analysis") and responsible for the delivery for two work packages (WP3 and WP4 terminology driven text mining and knowledge discovery application) in SPEEAK-PC collaboration project with TATA Steel funded by Innovative UK
- peer reviewer for academic journals / conferences / workshops, such as Journal of Natural Language Engineering, ESWC, USES, PLOS ONE
- providing cloud computing environment administration and maintenance for EU/National funded research projects and our group VMs for PhD research in the lab
- technical support for PhD students/colleagues (e.g., data collection via low-cost sensors, database systems, software engineering, web servers and service hosting)

Semantic R&D developer, Crownpeak (prev. ActiveStandards), London

Oct 2013 – Jan 2014

- Follow-up research and development of KTP project to build innovative semantic products on ActiveStandards platform, covering
 - Semantic Annotation & Indexing (GATE platform, Sesame/OWLIM 5.x (now GraphDB), Ontotext KIM platform)
 - Semantic technologies for Enterprise Information/content integration (Named Entity Recognition, entity linking, RDF, Ontology)
 - Semantic SEO and Web Compliance (corpus pre-processing & indexing, keywords extraction, RDFa, Web Accessibility)

KTP Associate, University of Westminster, London

Oct 2011 – Oct 2013

To undertake the Knowledge Transfer Partnership (KTP) objectives as defined in the KTP proposal covering the development of new semantic systems and services on ActiveStandards platform, in order to assist businesses and organizations to discover, understand and act on the actionable knowledge within their information repositories.

The R&D project (KTP project 007326) is funded by the UK Technology Strategy Board. I was the KTP associate and the lead R&D engineer in the project. The main technologies in this project covers the area of:

- Knowledge extraction (more specifically cross-domain NER and relation extraction with GATE),
- Knowledge management and retrieval (RDF, RDFS, OWL) with OWLIM-SE (now rebranded as GraphDB)
- Entity linking and knowlege base enrichment (via linked open data) and Enterprise Information Integration (ontology normalisation)
- Web compliance (SEO and fact checking)

I became Professional membership (990394505) of The British Computer Society (MBCS) since 2011.

The partnership project has been graded as second higher level which is shortlisted as one of KTP case-studies among 250 national funded projects.

Senior Software Engineer/Java developer, Dextrys, Suzhou, China

Aug 2006 – Jun 2010

- Engage in large scaled enterprise application development with complicated business requirements
- Involved projects include Chartis Brazil Insurance System, Trinity Project for Tripwire, Hanover Insurance
 system for Hanover, EA Back Office System for Electric Arts Inc., Mayban Fortis InsuranceSystem for
 eBaoTech.com, Non-Domestic management System for Hong Kong Housing Authority and Greece Reporting
 SMS System(GRSMS) for Proctor & Gamble
- Main duties
 - Design, enhance application solution and work closely with business analysis team
 - Transform clients' idea and business concepts into carefully designed and well-authorised software engineering solutions;
 - Work closely with UI design team to ensure the usability of the software;
 - Coordinate with QA Test Engineers on Module business testing, System Integration Test, Regression Test, and so forth during the whole software development lifecycle;

EDUCATION & RELEVANT COURSEWORK

M.S. in Web Technology, University of Southampton, Southampton, England

Sept 2011

- Thesis: "Linked Data based enterprise content management"
- Graduated with Merit
- Subject studies: Enterprise Web Development, Advance Topics on Web Services, Hypertext and Web technologies, Assistive Technologies and Universal Design, Intelligent Agent, Semantic Web Technologies, Rich Internet Applications.
- Skills developed: Enhanced the knowledge and understanding of important technologies and issues in designing
 and building enterprise web systems; decent English written and oral communication; research, interpretation
 and presentation; ability to analysis and evaluate issues regarding universal design and assistive technologies;
 Enhanced hands-on experience with building web services in Java; ability to design an agent-based system and
 evaluate the suitability of an agent-based approach to a given problem; Enhanced the ability to evaluate
 difference RIA technologies;

B.S. in Computer Science and Technology, Yancheng Institute of Technology, Yancheng, China

Sept 2006

- Dissertation: "Struts based online shopping system"
- Grade: 2:1

Certificates and Training

- Generative AI with Large Language Models (License RSKBJ5B8W4SM), Coursera(deeplearning.ai), Aug. 2023
- Convolutional Neural Networks (License <u>DWLCCDHKCE2N</u>), Coursera (deeplearning.ai), April 2018
- Structuring Machine Learning Projects (License <u>8JUA2EYXDHAN</u>), Coursera (deeplearning.ai), November 2017
- Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization (License K39M5D7B9Q6Z), Coursera (deeplearning.ai), November 2017
- Neural Networks and Deep Learning (License <u>BXJWXH56N6TZ</u>), Coursera (deeplearning.ai), October 2017
- Machine Learning (SoA 973756~189167), Stanford University through Coursera Inc., May 2015
- Data Mining with Weka, University of Waikato, August 2014
- Associate Certificate (License KTP007326-A02), UK Technology Strategy Board, Oct 2013
- M101J: MongoDB for Java Developers, "10gen, The MongoDB Company", July 2013
- Certified ScrumMasters (License 000285406), GoodAgile, Oct 2013
- 5th GATE Training Course Track 3 (Advanced GATE), University of Sheffield 2012
- CMI Level 5 in Management, Ashorne Hill Management College, 2011 2012

PUBLICATIONS

- Verschuuren, P. J., Gao, J., Van Eeden, A., Oikonomou, S., & Bandhakavi, A. (2023). Logically at Factify 2: A multi-modal fact checking system based on evidence retrieval techniques and transformer encoder architecture. In AAAI'23: De-Factify 2: 2nd Workshop on Multimodal Fact Checking and Hate Speech Detection, Washington, DC, USA. Access via https://ceur-ws.org/vol-3555/paper15.pdf
- Gao. J., Hoffmann, H. F., Oikonomou, S., Kiskovski, D., & Bandhakavi, A. (2022). "Logically at Factify 2022: Multimodal Fact Verification.", In: AAAI'22: First Workshop on Multimodal Fact-Checking and Hate Speech Detection, Vancouver, BC, Canada, access via arXiv preprint arXiv:2112.09253.
- Gao. J., Han S., Song X., Ciravegna, F. (2020). "RP-DNN: A Tweet level propagation context based deep neural networks for early rumor detection in Social Media", In: *The LREC 2020 Proceedings. The International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation*, 11-16 May 2020, Marseille. LREC 2020 (accepted for an Oral presentation).
- Han S., Gao, J., Ciravegna, F. (2019). "Neural Language Model Based Training Data Augmentation for Weakly Supervised Early Rumor Detection", *The 2019 IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social* Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM 2019), Vancouver, Canada, 27-30 August, 2019 [Acceptance Rate: 14%]
- Han S., Gao, J., Ciravegna, F. (2019). "Data Augmentation for Rumor Detection Using Context-Sensitive Neural Language Model With Large-Scale Credibility Corpus", Seventh International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) LLD, New Orleans, Louisiana, US
- Ciravegna, F., Gao, J., Ireson, N., Copeland, R., Walsh, J., & Lanfranchi, V. (2019, May). "Active 10: Brisk Walking to Support Regular Physical Activity." In Proceedings of the 13th EAI International Conference on Pervasive Computing Technologies for Healthcare (pp. 11-20). ACM.

- Ciravegna, F. Gao, J., Ingram, C., Ireson, N., Lanfranchi, V., & Humasak S. (2018). "Mapping Mobility to Support Crisis Management." 15th Proceeding of International Conference on Information Systems for Crisis Response and Management (ISCRAM). ISCRAM Association. 2018.
- Zhang, Z., Gao, J., & Ciravegna, F. (2018). SemRe-Rank: Incorporating Semantic Relatedness to Improve
 Automatic Term Extraction Using Personalized PageRank. ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from
 Data (TKDD).
- Yuan, Y., Gao, J., & Zhang, Y. (2017, October). Supervised Learning for Robust Term Extraction. In The proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Asian Language Processing (IALP). IEEE.
- Gao, Jie, and Suvodeep Mazumdar. "Exploiting linked open data to uncover entity types." In *Semantic Web Evaluation Challenge*, pp. 51-62. Springer International Publishing, 2015.
- Zhang, Z., Gao, J. and Ciravegna, F. (2016) <u>JATE2.0: Java Automatic Term Extraction with Apache Solr.</u> In: The LREC 2016 Proceedings. The International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation, 23-28 May 2016, Slovenia. LREC 2016.
- Zhang, Z., Gao, J., and Gentile, A.L. The LODIE team (University of Sheffield) Participation at the TAC2015
 Entity Discovery Task of the Cold Start KBP Track. In: Proceedings of the 2015 Text Analysis Conference. TAC
 Knowledge Base Population (KBP) 2015, 16-17 Nov 2015, Gaithersburg, Maryland USA.

SKILLS & ATTRIBUTES

- Strong written & oral communication, presentation and demonstrating skills with confident, articulate and professional speaking ability;
 - Two "Best Paper" award and invited talks in three workshops co-located with top AI conferences including ICLR 2019, AAAI 2022 & 2023
 - Deliver regular presentations and demonstrations in project meetings and international conferences with six invited presentations in the past few years.
 - O Work as PI in Europeana DSI-3 addendum project
 - Work as one of core developers (both mobile and backend server) and coordinator in PHE active10 project
 - Work as the sole associate & researcher in two Innovate UK (prev. TSB) funded projects for four years, both of which are rated as second higher score
- Strong collaborative mindset: able to communicate effectively with the diverse range of people and strong teamwork ability in multicultural and cross-disciplinary work environment.
 - Many years' experiences of actively and effectively working with data scientists, data engineers, data analysis, QA, MLops, other architects, business unit leaders, OSINT team, fact checking team, sales and product to help the organization adopt an AI-driven solution and ensure AI platforms deliver both business and technical requirements and harmonize the relationships among all the stakeholders @Logically;
 - Good team player with >10 years' experience in multicultural and cross-disciplinary working
 environment for both commercial and academic research projects funded by EU (<u>FP7</u>) and UK gov
 (e.g., <u>PHE</u>, <u>MoD</u>, <u>DIST</u>) @Sheffield.
 - Work as an embedded member of ActiveStandards team and as a <u>KTP associate</u> in Semantic Computing lab of University of Westminster to complete **two-years KTP project** with a series of challenging project milestones.
 - Work in large **EU projects** (WeSenseIt and SETA) involving partners from more than 5 countries
 - o Complete CMI Level 5 training in Management in Ashorne Hill Management College
 - o Trained as a Certified Scrum Master (CSM)
- Demonstrated thought leadership through self-direction, dynamism and adaptability:
 - Proven record of quickly adapting to new projects or tasks
 - Leading the ideation and write-ups of scientific papers, company white papers and research proposals (e.g., MoD DASA innovation funding) at Logically AI Innovation Solution team and one of core researchers in a number of EU and UK multi-million projects proposal writing (e.g., SETA);
 - Lead the conceptualization, development, and deployment of LLM projects tailored for misinformation & disinformation intelligence @Logically early 2023;
 - Leading Logically's participation in Multimodal Fact Verification (Factify) challenge at AAAI 2022 and AAAI 2023 (twice) and ranked first in leaderboard in 1ST workshop, ranked 3rd in 2nd workshop and "Best Paper" award;
 - Lead and manage rumor detection project in OAK group (Sheffield) and successfully delivered three scientific papers and opensource dataset published in top tier AI conferences (ICLR 2019, ASONAM 2019 and LREC 2020);
 - Researched and Developed a machine learning based entity typing algorithm in python and got 2nd place in OKE 2015 challenge in less than 2 months, despite no previous python experience

- Researched and Developed an end-to-end distant supervision learning based sentiment classifier for Italian in one month and further enhance the prototype as a commercial product for K-Now (a spin-out company from OAK Group) in 2015, despite no previous sentiment analysis experience
- Experience in Pytorch, Keras, LangChain, LlamaIndex, Numpy, scikit-learn, Python 3.x, Mlflow, Data Version Control (DVC), LLMs, Database (Faiss, Solr 5.x/6.x/7.x, Elasticsearch, MySQL 5.x, OWLIM/GraphDB, Sqlite), Web Service (Flask/fast.ai/unicorn/PM2, SOAP, WSDL, RESTful), NLTK, pytorch-geometric, Graph technique (igraph, networkx), Information Retrieval (Elasticsearch, Lucene, Apache Solr 5.x), ORM (Hibernate 3.x, SQLAlchemy), Java >6.x, Java EE, Spring 2.x/3.x (DI/IoC), Matlab, Javascript, NodeJS, HTTP Server(Flask, Tomcat 7.x), RDF framework (Sesame or Jena), Cloud computing (GCP, AWS, SolrCloud, Zookeeper, security),
- Good skills in agile methodologies: TDD (Junit, mockito), CI/CD (Bamboo, Jenkins)
 - More than 6 years commercial experience in an AGILE Scrum based environment (KTP project with ActiveStandards development team, PHE active10 @Sheffield, DS team@Logically AI)
- **Software/OS proficiency**: IntelliJ / PyCharm, Eclipse, Git, Docker, SVN, MATLAB, WEKA, GATE Platform, protégé, Linux/Ubuntu, AWS EC2, GCP, LaTex/Overleaf, Gephi
- Languages: Chinese (Native), English (working proficiency)
- Work eligibility: Settlement INDEFINITE LEAVE TO REMAIN